<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Rome, Venice, and Vienna, touching the present proceedinges of the Turkes against the Christians in Austria, Hungarie, and Heluetia, otherwise called Seuenbergh Also the true copie of a lamentable petition exhibited in the names of the afflicted Christians in those parts, to the Christian kingdomes in the vvest.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103468</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839221</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839221</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1255:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Rome, Venice, and Vienna, touching the present proceedinges of the Turkes against the Christians in Austria, Hungarie, and Heluetia, otherwise called Seuenbergh Also the true copie of a lamentable petition exhibited in the names of the afflicted Christians in those parts, to the Christian kingdomes in the vvest.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Danter, for Thomas Gosson, and are to be sold at his shop adioyning to London Bridge Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1, C4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648.</term>
               <term>Austria --  History --  1519-1740 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  HIstory --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEVVES FROM ROME, Venice, and Vienna, touching the preſent proceedinges of the Turkes againſt the Chriſtians in Auſtria, Hungarie, and Heluetia, otherwiſe called Seuenbergh.</p>
            <p>Alſo the true Copie of a Lamentable Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exhibited in the names of the afflicted Chriſtians in thoſe parts, to the Chriſtian Kingdomes in the VVeſt.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of an armoured knight with feathered helmet, lance, and spurs, on a horse with plumes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by Iohn Danter, for Thomas Goſſon, and are to be ſold at his ſhop adioyning to London Bridge Gate. 1595.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:2"/>
            <head>NEVVES FROM ROME, Venice, &amp; Vienna, touching the preſent proceedinges of the Turkes againſt the Chriſtians in Auſtria, Hungarie, and Heluetia, otherwiſe called Seuenbergh. Alſo the true Copie of a Lamentable Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exhibited in the names of the afflicted Chriſtians in thoſe parts, to the Chriſtian Kingdomes in the VVeſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ens vnbeléeuing harts haſten too late repentance, and the vnwillingneſſe of Chriſtians either to aſſiſt other, giues way for Infidels to inſult ouer all.</p>
            <p>Chriſts Prophecie is nowe performde, the daies waxe worſe and worſe, &amp; charitie is growne colde: For if mercie had had any gouernment among Chriſtian men, ſo many beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Townes, goodly Cities, glorious Kingdomes had not (as nowe they are) either béene vtterly made waſte, or ſuffered the woefull bondage of Turkiſh
<pb facs="tcp:3624:3"/> tyrannie. The flouriſhing Churches to which Chriſts Apoſtles writ, and in which they and the firſt Fathers of the Church laboured, are now the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles of vnhallowed multitudes, and onely a ſmall corner of the earth profeſſeth Chriſt. One Chriſtian ſuffering another to be as eaſilie conſumed, as an idle or enuious towneſman his neighbour helpleſly to be robbed or burned: Els had not all <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſome of <hi>Affricke,</hi> and ſo much of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſuffred ſo great and irrecouerable ſlauiſh bondage. Howe many goodly Nations the vnbeléeuing offſpring of <hi>Ottoman,</hi> haue ſubiected, ſufficiently too late experience expreſſeth, and the purpoſe of the common enemie to ſubiect the reſt, immediate proofe explaineth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath</hi> now Emperour of <hi>Turkey,</hi> glorying in the vſurped ſeate of the Greekiſh Emperre, not long ſince ſubiected by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amurath</hi> his predeceſſour, ambitiouſly by his tyrannous Baſſaes incited, hath attempted the affliction of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the vnconquered part of <hi>Hungarie, Poland, Heluetia,</hi> and other Kingdomes neighbouring <hi>Greece,</hi> whoſe procéedinges ſince the 25. of December laſt, till the middle of Ianuarie, this ſmall Pamphlet handleth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rab</hi> is a towne néere <hi>Donow</hi> in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> which in the end of the laſt Harueſt, the Turkes violently after long ſiege entred, ſparing neither age nor ſexe, but making the Infants daies equall with the aged Elders, both young and old by their crueltie at once periſhed. The winning of which place hath not ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weakned the other Forts of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians power. After they had tyrannouſly inſulted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Rab,</hi> they immediatlie bent their forces againſt <hi>Comar,</hi> the people of which Citie aſſiſted by the hand of God, and reſolued rather to die than ſubiect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſlauerie of Infidels, valiantly defended
<pb facs="tcp:3624:3"/> themſelues, and violently compelled, the huge multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Turkes to raiſe their ſiege and retire to <hi>Rab</hi> which they had lately taken. From ſundry parts of Chriſtendome ſince the 25. of December theſe certaine and vnreprooueable intelligences haue béene ſent: <hi>videlicet,</hi> it is certified from Rome the laſt of Ianuarie.</p>
            <p>The Emperours Maieſties Legates had audience before the Pope, who deſired a ſubſidie ſhould be leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Cleargie, for the cutting off of an Arme of the Riuer of <hi>Donow,</hi> that falls in by <hi>Comar,</hi> thereby not only to defend the ſaid towne and the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, but alſo to hinder the Turkes from enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>Oouen:</hi> and beſides it would bee a meane to ſpare many Souldiers that muſt be imployed in theſe parts. To this the Pope condiſcended; with promiſe to aide the Emperour with all he might. <hi>Iuſtiniano</hi> is appointed the Collector.</p>
            <p>The ſame time alſo it was certified that the great Maſter of <hi>Malta</hi> was reconciled, béeing authoriſed from the Pope to be accountable to no Eſtate.</p>
            <p>It is alſo concluded, that the Prince of <hi>Seuenbergh,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Heluetia,</hi> vpon whoſe burden the firſt war betwéene the Turkes and Chriſtians muſt néedes lye, ſhall haue 20000. Crownes monthly to maintaine the warre, and if (which God forbid) he be expulſed <hi>Heluetia,</hi> he ſhall haue ſome dominion allotted him in the Emperie and 200000. crownes yearely.</p>
            <p>Moreouer at <hi>Rome</hi> the ſame day arriued this newes, that the Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo</hi> in Spaine, being ninetie foure yeares of age deceaſed, and left behinde him a Million of readie money, halfe a Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in debts, and ſixe hundred thouſand Crownes in Plate, Roabes, coſtly apparrell and other Iewels:
<pb facs="tcp:3624:4"/> Making fiue Executors; of which the King of Spain is principall, who hath obtained that his money ſhould be imployed to the Churches vſe, ſéeing the ſaide Archbiſhop had bequeathed nothing to his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, whom belike he prouided for in his life time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alberto</hi> the Cardinall ſuccéeding in the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke and poſſeſſing theſe goods, hath granted halfe of them to be imployed againſt the Turkes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Venice <date>the 13. of Ianuarie.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>LEtters came from <hi>Syria,</hi> certifiying, the <hi>Sycalla</hi> or Admirall with the Gallies are come to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, and that a great <hi>Armatho</hi> is prouiding againſt <hi>Hungarie</hi> by Sea.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe certefied to that ſtate of <hi>Venice</hi> from <hi>Halow,</hi> by reaſon of the great froſt and ſnowe, the Cytrons, Lymons, Oringes, and ſuch frute were all ſpoiled, that woulde bee great impeachment to the Turkes prouiſion.</p>
               <p>Alſo the eleuenth of Ianuarie there came a Poſt from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Venice,</hi> that certified them of the French Kings hurt: and the ſame Poſt ſaide, that as he paſſed on his way by Lyons, he heard of ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion at <hi>Marſilles,</hi> whence ſundrie Noble men are fled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the 11. of Ianuarie.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>AT fiue of the Clocke that day in the morning, came theſe ill newes: that eight hundred Turks ſome on foote but moſt part horſe, came from <hi>Rab</hi> to ſaint <hi>Georgen,</hi> and that the fift daie of this ſaid month the Turkes had taken <hi>Prûg</hi> nere <hi>Leyten,</hi> and burned the Cities and Country of the Lord <hi>Herryth,</hi> making
<pb facs="tcp:3624:4"/> excurſions within eight myles of <hi>Vienna,</hi> murdring the people, or making them ſlaues, robbing, ſpoiling and burning the whole Countrey, and threatening within few daies to gather head againſt <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe the ſaid 11. of Ianuarie, a Gouernour of horſemen (being in a Hold hard by) required to haue aid: and the Magiſtrates of <hi>Vienna</hi> haue taken order that euerie Citizen (according to his abilitie) ſhould kéepe a proportion of horſe and footmen, till other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration may be made.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Graue Hardigh</hi> beeing taken priſoner by the Turkes, ſought to breake priſon, his brother hauing prouided a ladder of roapes for his eſcape, and fortie horſe for his reſcue: but it was diſcouered, and they all ſlaine or taken.</p>
               <p>Thrée ſodaine fiers haue béen lately in <hi>Vienna,</hi> yet by Gods great mercie but one houſe at a time burnt: neuertheleſſe the fearfull multitude conſter it to be an ominous preſage of ſad miſfortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Prage <date>the 10. of Ianuarie.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THis day the Emperours Ambaſſadours returned to <hi>Prage,</hi> from the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: That the <hi>Polonians</hi> would willingly aſſiſt the Emperour, vpon condition the Emperour would doo aſmuch for him, if the Turke ſhould moue warre vpon <hi>Polonia:</hi> of which to be reſolued, hee requireth the Princes Electors, to ſend their Ambaſſadours to his Parliament holden in <hi>Polonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximilian</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> intends to bée Generall againſt the Turkes. <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Manſfield</hi> will come with 3000. horſmen, one thouſand of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being bard, and two Regiments of foote of 6000, are promiſed out of the lower <hi>Germanie</hi> to bee ſent into
<pb facs="tcp:3624:5"/> 
                  <hi>Hungarie</hi> with all ſpéede.</p>
               <p>This tenth of Ianuarie a Legate came to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour at <hi>Prage,</hi> with foure demands from Charles the Duke: firſt for neceſſaries concerning his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and relief for thrée yeares, till the warres were ſomewhat quieted in <hi>Hungarie.</hi> Secondly, that hée be taken as a Seſſor or Prince in the Emperie, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated in the Kingdome of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that if he died without iſſue male, his lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Moldau, Walachia,</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> ſhall come to the ſuccéeding Kings of <hi>Hungarie.</hi> Thirdly, that the Emperour would ſend him foure thouſand horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at his proper charge. Fourthly, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhould not enter into peace with the Turke, without his knowledge. But what the Emperour reſolues to anſwere is not yet knowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Vienna <date>the 6. of Ianuarie.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe laſt night in the euening <hi>Syfrid van Colneyt</hi> ſent his ſeruant to <hi>Vienna,</hi> certifiyng the State that the Turks and Tartars in great numbers were come ouer the paſſage at <hi>Altenbergh,</hi> and fired a towne called ſaint <hi>Peters,</hi> and remained that night at ſaint <hi>Iohns.</hi> But the day before they were at ſaint <hi>Nicholas, Sturne, Cabaſtain, Somerain, Zuiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> and other neighbouring places betweene <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbergh</hi> and <hi>Prage,</hi> and he feared, they had taken ſome of thoſe places, ſpoyled the people, and hazarded <hi>Altenbergh,</hi> by reaſon there was but two hundred men at Armes therein, the enemie beeing twentie thouſand ſtrong, and very well furniſhed with all munition.</p>
               <p>Preſently the ſame day came another meſſenger, certifiyng that the enemie is come to <hi>Prage</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:3624:5"/> 
                  <hi>Men eſhoffen,</hi> firing many townes, killing multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people, and taking diuers priſoners, ſo that <hi>Altenbergh</hi> is in great danger to be taken away, as <hi>Rab.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>More from Vienna <date>the 8. of Ianuarie.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THE ſeconde of this month came the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours from <hi>Seuenbergh,</hi> the chiefe mans name beeing <hi>Bapteri Iſtuan,</hi> accompanied with them of <hi>Moldau,</hi> and were lodged at the Lorde of <hi>Weſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers,</hi> next day they had audience before <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperours brother.</p>
               <p>About foure a clocke in the afternoone they came to <hi>Iohn de Medices,</hi> and the fourth day iourneyed to <hi>Prage</hi> to the Emperour.</p>
               <p>Two daies after came tydinges that fiftéene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Turkes were come to <hi>Rab</hi> with intention to take <hi>Altenbergh,</hi> which they may eaſily doo, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the riuers are ſo extreamely frozen, and the helpe ſo ſmall.</p>
               <p>Preſently after came worſe newes, that foure and twenty thouſand Turkes were entred <hi>Auſtria:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that euening euery thirtith man was choſen in that Citie, beſide the quarter of <hi>Vienna Wald,</hi> who were muſtred the ſeauenth of this month at <hi>Brûg</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Leyther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the laſt Parlament, all things ſtand as before, but the enemie growes very ſtrong, our ſouldiers for want of pay beeing vnwilling to ſerue: Certaine of the Generall of <hi>Seeneberghs</hi> ſouldiers mutening for want of pay, are gone vpward into the Emperie, and will make vs haue a very ill name: The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which they receiued, they left word ſhould pay for their horſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3624:6"/>
               <p>One of my Lord the Dukes ſeruaunts, that was ſent to the Lord <hi>Haunce Wererne,</hi> Generall for the Margraue of <hi>Bourgan</hi> toward <hi>Nyſadell,</hi> brought ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that the Turkes and Tartars did great harme thereabout, none reſiſting them, the people onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of flight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Presbergh, <date>the laſt of December.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Embaſſadors of <hi>Seuenbergh</hi> yeſterday about twelue a clocke arriued heere, and immediatelye went toward <hi>Fiſhau.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Spies bring certaine tidings, that the Turks gather in manie thouſands about <hi>Rab,</hi> meaning to ſpoyle the Countrey about <hi>Vienna,</hi> for whom they make here great prouiſion.</p>
               <p>The 25. of this month the Turkes ſet forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Seinneyt</hi> in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> but the people of the Country ſo fiercely aſſailed them, that there remaind aboue an hundred dead on the place, beſide a number that were drowned in flight. Some Turkiſh priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that were there taken, confeſſed, that the Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaes purpoſe immediately after Newyeares day to doo ſome great exployt.</p>
               <p>This laſt of December, one of our Embaſſadors came from <hi>Seuenbergh,</hi> certifying vs the Prince of <hi>Seuenbergh</hi> greatly endamageth the Turke, taking from him one Hold after another. And that he hath thrée goodly Campes, one lead by <hi>Herbart Michael</hi> beyond the <hi>Donow,</hi> to hinder the Turkes paſſage to <hi>Oouen:</hi> the other by <hi>Iſtuan Ferran</hi> in <hi>Lucar,</hi> neere <hi>Tamuſweer:</hi> the third by <hi>Cornus Iaſper</hi> from <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyt:</hi> to whom are adioyned of the vpper <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and Gréekiſh Souldiers, fifteene hundred men at
<pb facs="tcp:3624:6"/> armes. What their expedition will ſort vnto, is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the hands of God: and of their ſucceſſe we looke ſhortly to heare from <hi>Caſſau.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Caſſau, <date>December the 28.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Turkes and Tartars gather daylie in great multitudes about <hi>Iula,</hi> lead by the Baſſa of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſweer,</hi> and the Baſſa of <hi>Selnicke,</hi> deſirous to doo ſome ſeruice (while the <hi>Teyſca</hi> and other waters are froſen) againſt <hi>Tartaſail</hi> by <hi>Teyny.</hi> Againſt whom the Chriſtians on our ſide make head, looking for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge which way they intend to take, and being aſſured of their march, wee will with them of <hi>Seuenbergh</hi> méete them, committing our ſelues to God, in whoſe quarrell wee willingly lay downe our liues, hoping he will defend his diſtreſſed and afflicted flocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>More from Caſſau <date>the laſt of December.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Turkes and Tartars perreyuing our inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ioyne with the <hi>Seuenberghers,</hi> are for all theyr great multitudes, fearfully retyred. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe doubting their ſodaine returne, wee kéepe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie carefull watch.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:7"/>
            <head>The Confesſion of a Tartarian Horſeman taken amongſt other Priſoners.</head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of an armoured knight with feathered helmet, lance, and spurs, on a horse with plumes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt hee ſaith, although the Turkiſh Emperour commaunded them to win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> they notwithſtanding went forwarde, hearing their owne Countrey was afflicted, and ſending ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene
<pb facs="tcp:3624:7"/> thouſand men before, they were all ſlaine and taken by the Chriſtians of <hi>Seuenbergh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Alſo hee ſaith, that the King of <hi>Tartars</hi> ſonne, with the reſt of the Armie lye about <hi>Tamuſweer</hi> and <hi>Weſenbergh,</hi> and that of the <hi>Tartars</hi> onely two thouſand ſhall remaine there.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Alſo he ſaith, that in the laſt ſkirmiſh thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Tartars,</hi> and one hundred <hi>Turkes,</hi> all horſemen, were ſent to learne if the riuer of <hi>Rabnitz</hi> were hard frozen to paſſe or no, but what they haue done hée knowes not, for by the ſtumbling of his horſe he was taken priſoner: but he thinketh they meant to ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>Capurar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, hee knoweth not what number of men were at <hi>Cappa,</hi> but at <hi>Rab</hi> there were ſome fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene thouſand.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Fifthly hee ſaith, that no more <hi>Tartars</hi> muſt come downe, but thoſe that are there, are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſet vpon <hi>Erlaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Sixthly he faith, all thoſe <hi>Turkes</hi> that came laſt from Sea, beeing about fiftie thouſand, are all peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Seuenthly hee ſaith, the <hi>Turke</hi> hath made peace with the <hi>Perſian,</hi> but becauſe the <hi>Souldans</hi> ſonne is dead at <hi>Perto,</hi> he knoweth not whether the peace will holde.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Eighthly hee ſaith, hee knoweth not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3624:8"/> the Souldan will hold warre againſt the <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geani</hi> or no.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Ninthly hee ſaith, At <hi>Comar</hi> the Chriſtians ſlue nine hundred Ianiſſaries: but at <hi>Rab</hi> hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not how manie were ſlaine, onely he remembreth that ſome daies thrée, ſome dayes foure, and ſome dayes fiue hundred periſhed.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Laſtly hee ſaith, The men of <hi>Comar</hi> ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auntly reſiſted, that the Turkes were not able to continue their ſiege, but were forced to retyre barke againe to <hi>Rab.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:8"/>
            <head>The true Copie of a Lamentable Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exhibited in the names of the afflicted Chriſtians in the Eaſt parts, to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kingdomes in the VVeſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F either humane pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (naturally graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in mans heart) to compaſſionate the oppreſſed, or the ſweete bandes of Chriſtian Loue wherein you &amp; we (members of one head) are mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound either to other: haue anie power to intreate your hartie praiers or ſpeedie help: we humbly beg the one, and beſeech the other.</p>
            <p>You happie Princes of peopled Kingdomes, and bleſſed people of thoſe happie Princes: commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (for CHRISTES cauſe) our miſerable diſtreſſe, that haue no day of happines, no night of reſt: but feare within, and terror without, dimmes the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our day, and doubles the darknes of our night. We heare, (which addeth heauineſſe to our greefe) that ciuill warres, priuate quarrells, and vnchriſtian malice, weakneth the Arme of Chriſtendome, that ſhould be ſtrengthened among you. Alas, what need yee (like the earth-bred brethren) maliciouſly let
<pb facs="tcp:3624:9"/> cut each others blood? when ye haue a whole world of enemies to warre againſt: and wee and you in all but a corner of the earth to oppoſe our ſelues againſt their crueltie.</p>
            <p>VVe heare how you prouoke (as wee haue done) by the exceſſe of ſinne, Gods wrathfull and heauie vengeance. Let our pride, be a preſident for you to learne humblenes: our neglect of God, a warning that you leaue ſuch negligence: our wrath, enuie, and auarice, a meane to make you milde, louing and liberall: our ſloth, wantonnes and exceſſe, to increaſe your diligence, chaſtitie and temperance. Now for our rich array we put on ſackcloath, our beauteous Ladies ſit with teare-diſtained faces, our Virgines ſing not the Hymnes of gladnes, but of ſorrow, our Old-men faint feebly in the ſtreete, and our Yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men prepare themſelues to venture their precious liues in open field,</p>
            <p>Dere Chriſtian Brethren, turne turne your pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eyes vppon our proſtrate miſerie. Remember the willingnes of your fore-fathers in that great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> vnder the leading of <hi>Godfrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Bulloigne.</hi> Then Princes, Noblemen, and well diſpoſed people, came in perſon from the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt VVeſterne Kingdomes, euen from <hi>England, France, Netherland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> the women gaue the ſouldiers their bracelets of gold and ſiluer, yea, poore ſeruants offred of their ſmall wages to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that holy VVarre. Ah, where is that pitie, care, true loue and mercie now become? The Turkiſh &amp; vnbeleeuing Enemies are come by manie Kingdoms farre neerer your homes, and your commiſeration is by manie degrees farther off. Let <hi>Antioch,</hi> the firſt Citie wherein the name of Chriſtians began (nowe made a Synagogue of vnbeleeuing Infidels) moue
<pb facs="tcp:3624:9"/> ye to compaſsion. The Candleſtickes are remoued from the Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> prophecied: the light of Chriſtianitie is wholly extinct among them. In <hi>Syria</hi> Chriſts Spouſe hath loſt her beautie. In the Emperie of <hi>Greece,</hi> Kingdomes of <hi>Epyrus, Lyſtria, Crete, Cyprus,</hi> and other the Mediterranean Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, CHRIST had (&amp; that within theſe few yeres) his beloued Vineyard, planted, tended, wel dreſſed, compaſſed about. But now the Turkes (like wilde Boares are entred, the Vineyard is waſted. In ſtead of wine, the earth (in all thoſe and diuers other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes) is drunke with Chriſtian blood: and there is no face of Chriſtianitie left, no outward Church. Let that part of our Kingdomes alreadie loſt, &amp; the reſt now hazarding, win ye to ſome compaſsion.</p>
            <p>But it may be, becauſe the Turke is farre off, you thinke he neuer can haue power to hurt ye, you and your children ſhall be ſafe. Be not ſo groſe conceip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Conſider, wee had Fathers that gathered for vs, ſo had the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and other the forenamed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but now their welth and ours lies open to the Enemie. VVe had houſes, but Turkes poſſes them: Pallaces, but they are ſpoyled: Churches, but they are prophaned: Cities, but they are waſted: &amp; ſome more we haue, but how long they ſhalbe ours, we li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle know. And yet within theſe few yeres, wee were thrice farther off from daunger than you now are. Neither flatter your ſelues that your Countryes are populous, your Cities ſtrong, your Kingdomes fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the Sea: they and we had peopled King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, fenced Cities, ſea-walled Ilands, but all was vaine, they were ſingled one by one, their neighbors denied them helpe, and firſt they, then thoſe deniers periſhed. Such will our caſe be, if we be not aided: ſuch will yours be, if ye doo not aid vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:10"/>
            <p>Beſides, there is a rumour ſpred in ſome partes of Chriſtendome, how the Turkes are iuſt in keeping faith and promiſe. O fond and idle beliefe: What faith can they keepe that haue no faith?</p>
            <p>Such faith as not long ſince they kept with that noble Chriſtian Prince of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> the Turkiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himſelfe paſſing his word vnto him. When that moſt Princely Chriſtian VVarriour, had defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Famagoſta</hi> till all munition and vittaile failed: hee and his ſmall companie yet worthely reſoluing, intended deerely to ſel their liues, and ſtood valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to defend the breaches. The Turke ſeeing their reſolution, offred the Prince, that if hee would ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render the Citie, himſelfe and the ſouldiers, wyth theyr Armes, weapons, and colours diſplaied, the Princeſſe with her children, the other women, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and children of the Citie with bag and baggage ſhould paſſe quietly through the Turkes Armie, and bee tranſported to what Hauen in Chriſtendome they deſired. The Prince accepted theſe conditions, the Turkiſh Emperor confirmed them with an: oath: but (like a falſe miſcreaunt) when they were iſſued, hee compelled the Prince and the able men to beare burthens of earth vppon their ſhoulders to repayre the breaches: then commaunded the Princeſſe, her children, the women and other weake people (after manie ſhamefull abuſes) to be cruelly tortured to death. Then ſtripped they the Souldiers and chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them for ſlaues. Laſtly they puld out the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Princes eyes, punched his warlike bodie full of hoales, and hangd him on the top maſt of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall Galley, more to afflict his poore ſubiects that rowed there as ſlaues.</p>
            <p>Such faith will they keepe as with the laſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Greece</hi> they did: whom (after many frendly
<pb facs="tcp:3624:10"/> ſeeming Ambaſſades) they ſodainly beſieged in his chiefe Citie <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and in the chiefe Gate of that Citie, he and his children were found mangled wyth manie wounds, and trampled with their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes feete.</p>
            <p>Such faith will they keepe as lately they did wyth vs of <hi>Hungarie:</hi> Hauing taken certaine yongmen of noble Families. Wee laboured for their libertie to the Baſſa of <hi>Buda.</hi> Their ranſome was ſet downe, and licenſe granted for their frends to bring it. The Baſſa himſelfe receiued it: and then tyrannouſlie to ſeuerall ſtakes he tyed the miſerable yong Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men naked, and in preſence of their friends cauſed their bodies to be ſliced with ſharpe kniues, the fleſh caſt vnto hungrie dogs, and the dead carcaſſes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered their ſorrowfull friends for the raunſome they had paid.</p>
            <p>This is the Turkiſh faith, this their vow, this their religion: let no Chriſtian State beleeue them, nor for lucre hold league with them, for they doo await time firſt to deſtroy vs, then to extirpate them.</p>
            <p>What ſhould wee ſay that you cannot conceiue, looke on your Cities, Pallaces, Fieldes, Meadowes, walkes, pleaſant Gardens, thinke ours were like yours, but nowe are nothing but receptacles of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Looke on your wiues and beauteous daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and remember that we haue ſuch (though not ſo fortunate) yours ſafe, ours ſubiect to rauiſhment and ſpoile. Looke on your ſonnes and forget not ours, of whom no ſmall number are alreadie with their wofull fathers chained in Turkiſh ſlauerie, the reſt oppoſing themſelues againſt their tyrannie. And then remember it is in his quarrell wee ſtriue, that hath promiſed to reward a cup of colde water giuen in his name: much more reward againe with tenne
<pb facs="tcp:3624:11"/> folde bleſſings, your Chriſtian mercie and pittie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs.</p>
            <p>To him that is able to helpe as well by one as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, we commit ourſelues: and commend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our miſerable eſtate to your Chriſtian Charities.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Prage,</hi> 
                  <date>the 13, of Ianuarie.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your poore afflicted Chriſtian Bretheren of</hi> Boheme, Hungarie, Auſtria, Polonia, <hi>and</hi> Heluetia.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London by Iohn Danter, for Thomas Goſſon, and are to be ſold at his ſhop adioyning to London Bridge Gate. 1595.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3624:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
